"Naturally Boosting AMPK
with Exercise for Life Extension"
How can we naturally boost
the enzyme AMPK
to slow aging
without starving ourselves?
AMPK is activated
by a fuel shortage.
If we don't want to limit
the amount of energy
going in through our mouths,
then we have to ramp up
the amount of energy
going out through our muscles.
Put people on a bike and start
taking muscle biopsies
while they cycle,
and you can detect a near
tripling of AMPK activation
within twenty minutes
in both diabetics
and nondiabetics.
That makes sense.
The muscles use up
the ATP to contract,
so AMP builds up
and AMPK is activated.
That may be one of the ways
exercise leads to weight loss.
AMPK activation also leads
to mitochondrial biogenesis,
meaning the formation
of extra mitochondria,
the power plants
within our cells
where fat is burned
and ATP is created.
So, AMPK doesn't
just cause more fat
to be shoveled
into the furnace,
it also causes more furnaces
to be built.
In this way, AMPK helps explain
why endurance training
eventually enables us
to run faster and farther.
So, might an AMPK activator
be like
the fabled exercise-in-a-pill?
Indeed, AMPK activation
can dramatically enhance
performance.
An AMPK-activator drug given
to sedentary mice for a month
boosted their running endurance
by 44 percent.
After one such drug
was discovered
at the famed Tour de France,
AMPK activators were banned
by the World Anti-Doping Agency.
So not just fasting in a pill,
but an exercise mimetic too?
People are often
"unwilling to perform
even a minimum
of physical activity..."
wrote a group
of pharmacologists,
"thus, indicating that drugs
mimicking endurance exercise
are highly desirable."
The "mass appeal" of such a drug
may tempt "big pharma"
to view physical inactivity
as a market to be medicalized
for profit."
But that vision
pales in comparison
to the universal market
for an anti-aging remedy.
In his essay
"On youth and old age,"
the Greek philosopher Aristotle
described death
as the loss of inner heat.
Indeed, the progressive loss
of function
of the estimated 10 million
billion mitochondria
spread throughout the body
is considered a core tenet
of the biology of aging,
but mitochondrial dysfunction
isn't just a consequence
of aging,
but one of its causes.
Dysfunctional mitochondria are
thought to actively contribute
to the aging process,
an insight illustrated
by a pioneering experiment
published over 30 years ago.
If you inject mitochondria
from a young animal
into a human cell,
nothing happens.
The cell doesn't appear
to notice.
Human skin cells average
about 300 mitochondria each,
and adding 10 to 15 extras
from a young rat
didn't appear
to have any effect.
But add the same number
of mitochondria from an old rat,
and the human cells start
showing signs of degeneration
within just a few days.
Even just having a few percent
of those old mitochondria
was enough to drive
the human cells
to an early grave.
So, age-impaired mitochondria
don't just become
less efficient,
but may become actively harmful.
So, if centenarian-equivalent
rat mitochondria are so toxic,
how do centenarian
human cells survive?
A group of Italian researchers
took some centenarian
skin biopsies to find out.
Skin samples
taken from the forearms
of young individuals
were compared to those
of elderly individuals.
As expected, each mitochondrial
mite from the older cells
was comparatively defective,
less efficient,
leaking free radicals.
But to the scientists' surprise,
the total amount of ATP
the centenarian cells
were pumping out
was even greater
than that of the younger cells.
How is that possible?
Because of a bulked up
mitochondrial mass.
It's like if an older Mike Tyson
took on a featherweight.
Even if pound-for-pound
the whipper-snapper's biceps
were more energy-generating,
Mike's sheer muscular mass
might prevail.
So how did the centenarian
mitochondria get swole?
AMPK.
Mitochondria can take up
anywhere between 2 percent
and 50 percent
of the volume of a cell
and are in constant motion,
merging together
and splitting apart
like the molten wax
of a lava lamp.
In times of starvation
or stress,
the fusing of individual
mitochondria together
into a large tubular network
can be advantageous,
in part by diluting
the effects
of damaged mitochondria
by mixing their contents
in with others.
AMPK appears to accomplish this
by tipping the lava lamp balance
from fission to fusion
by blocking
one of the proteins
necessary to break mitochondria
back apart.
This is thought
to be one of the routes
by which endurance exercise
can rejuvenate
mitochondrial function.
Thanks to AMPK,
working out may magnify
your mitochondria
as well as your muscles.
Our mitochondrial function
does decline with age,
in part through
the impaired ability of AMPK
to generate new mitochondria,
but AMPK can build
new cellular power plants,
expand existing ones,
and decommission old ones
(so-called mitophagy).
AMPK is said to serve
as a "mitochondrial guardian,"
and in that role
may help guard against
the ravages
of age-related disease.
If an AMPK activating drug
really could help us
reap the fat-burning
and health-promoting benefits
of fasting and exercise
without the hunger and sweat,
one could imagine
how it would become
one of the best-selling drugs
on the planet.
And it is.
It's called metformin,
prescribed more
than 90 million times a year
in the U.S. alone.
But should we all be taking it
to prolong our lives?
That's what
I'll be covering next.